Good, today's דף daf is צדי זין Tzadi Zayin 97, and we
pick up in the משנה mishna in the middle of צדי ו
עמוד ב, Tzadi Vav Amud Bet, and we are continuing with גזילה
gezeila issues. The first big משנה mishna had to do with קנייני
גזילה kinyanei gezeila and this משנה mishna continues it, and let's take
a look. גזל בהמה והזקינה, gazal beheima vehizkina, this was quoted before,
somebody steals an animal and it gets old, עבדים והזקינו, avadim vehizkinu,
and slaves and they get old, משלם כשעת הגזילה, mesham kesha'as hagezeila,
you pay according to the time that it was stolen. And again,
as I mentioned the other day, the big question here is, you
know, it sounds like it's at your קונה kona the slave and
you're קונה kona the animal with a שינוי, shinui, and now you
have to pay based on the value of what it was when
you stole it. But there's another possibility here, which is not really
being fully explored in the גמרא, Gemara, which is maybe you give
back the slave and the animal, maybe it's not enough of a
שינוי shinui for you to be קונה kona it, it's still the
same slave and the same animal, just older, but maybe you pay
the difference, maybe it's an animal that's worth less. So the fact
that there might be a space between the idea of שינוי קונה,
shinui kona, of taking of owning it as opposed to like there's
like three, there's like, we're going to see in the משנה, mishna,
there's like, you know,
there's like here is הרי שלך לפניך, harey shelcha lifnecha,
you give the same thing back and you say it's unchanged, okay?
It's effectively unchanged even if it's worth less, we don't really notice
that it's changed and you're able to give it back to the
owner. And over here you have שינוי קונה, shinui kona, okay? It's
a different object, okay? Now there's a lot of space in between
those two. There's something that actually like that's a continuum, right? Isn't
there things here that and actually it's changed and you can't say
oh I'm just giving you back the same thing, but it's not
enough of a different object that you should be קונה kona it?
Okay, so that's not explored in the משנה, mishna, but something like
a slave that gets old or an animal that gets old, does
that mean it's so different that you own it? Or does that
mean no, you can't say הרי שלך לפניך, harey shelcha lifnecha, you
can't say look it's the same object I took from you, it's
not the same, it's older, it's worth a lot less, pay the
difference, okay? So the idea that there would actually be a possibility
you'd give back the object and pay the difference as opposed to
owning the object or giving it back and paying nothing makes a
lot of sense and it's possible that's the case in the משנה.
mishna. The משנה mishna doesn't say you own the slave or you
own the old animal, it just says you have to pay according
to the original value. Maybe that means pay the difference, right? But
that is not really explicitly explored, but logically that's a category that
makes a lot of sense. Okay, so anyway, that's what the משנה
mishna says, that you say that you have to pay based on
the original value, which again either means you're קונה kona it and
you pay the amount when it was you stole it or you
give it back and you pay the difference. רבי מאיר אומר, Rabbi
Meir omer, בעבדים אומר לו הרי שלך לפניך, ba'avadim omer lo harey
shelcha lifnecha,
slaves are like קרקע, karka, they're not stolen and therefore once you
give back the slave you don't have to pay the difference. There's
never an act of גזילה gezeila that makes you liable for the
value. It's just not your object so give it back, okay? But
if it's the but basically you can go ahead and presumably according
to that let's say the slave died, would you say well I
never stole it, there's no such idea of stealing, there's no גזילה
gezeila by slaves? Okay, so or it's already so therefore you can
always like give it back and not have to pay anything.
Okay, גזל מטבע ונסדק, gazal matbe'a venistak, now let's say you stole
a coin that it got a crack in it, פירות והרקיבו, peiros
vehirkivu,
or fruits that rotted, יין והחמיץ, yayin vehichmitz, wine that
became that became vinegar, משלם כשעת הגזילה, mesham kesha'as hagezeila,
so you pay again the full amount. You can't give the object
back. Does that mean you give it back and you pay the
difference? These types of cases would seem like the object really has
completely changed, so maybe you own the object and you pay the
full amount, okay? But you can't just give it back and be
exempt. Now מטבע ונפסל, matbe'a venifsal, תרומה ונטמאת, truma venitmeis,
let's say you stole a coin and it did not physically crack,
it just that it had been invalidated by the government, the government
had issued new coins, or תרומה truma and it became טמא, tamei,
so it's now has no not no use, you can burn it
and use it get benefit as you're burning it, but it's obviously
worth a trivial amount, but it's not a visible damage, right? It
just became טמא, tamei, you can't see the טומאה, tumah, חמץ עבר
עליו הפסח, hametz avar alav hapesach, or חמץ chametz a big and
now
that really is worthless after פסח, Pesach, okay? But it's not of
damage that's visible, that's היזק שאינו ניכר, hezek she'eino nikar, non-visible damage,
okay? בהמה ונעבדה בה עבירה, beheima veni'avda ba aveira,
or an animal that was used for an act of bestiality, an
act of sexual transgression, that can now not be brought as
a
sacrifice, okay? Which again is a minimum damage, but anyway, but the
common denominator of all these things is that it's a non-visible damage.
או שנפסלה מעל גבי המזבח, o shenifsela me'al gabey hamizbeach, or
I guess נעבדה בה עבירה ni'avda ba aveira might be that there
actually is witnesses to it. and then it would be stoned, so
that would be a case that would be worthless. Okay, נעבד בעבירה,
ne'evad be'averah, being invalid for the altar is that there are not
witnesses, but it’s still because this act was done cannot be used
as a korban or another example that it becomes invalid for the
altar would be that there's like some type of a blemish. In
all these cases, או שהיתה יוצא להיסקל, o shehayta yotza lehiskel, it
was a שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, and it was going to be
stoned. In all these cases אומר לו הרי שלך לפניך, omer lo
harei shelcha lefanecha, look, it’s your thing, looks the same, it’s the
same object that I stole. So the end is definitely a big
חידוש chiddush where the object is worth very little or worth zero,
but nevertheless because it’s not visible you can essentially say I’m giving
you back the same object and I satisfied my obligation, I returned
the object, even though now you have something that’s worthless. Okay, that’s
a big חידוש. chiddush. But again the question at the beginning of
the משנה mishnah is, does the beginning of the משנה mishnah mean
to say all these things mentioned are שינוי shinuy and you are
קונה? koneh? Or all these things are different enough that you can’t
say הרי שלך לפניך? harei shelcha lefanecha? That you can’t say I
did nothing, it’s the same thing. It changed, it’s not in the
same condition and therefore you have to pay the difference. Okay, so
again that’s the issue that is not being addressed, which is is
it that you are
not קונה koneh it but you give it back and pay the
difference? Or is it that you are קונה koneh it and you
pay the amount it was when you stole it? Yes, Charlie. Yeah,
question. The coin that has been invalidated could still be melted down.
Right, I was wondering about that. I mean the גמרא gemara anyway
is going to discuss how bad נפסלה nifselah is in general and
that is correct. You still do have the raw value. Now that
might be the fact that it's not worthless, a lot of these
things aren't worthless, right? Something that can’t be used on the מזבח
mizbe'ach is not worthless. It’s worth less, but it’s not worth zero,
right? So that’s right. So that is the question. And the חמץ
chametz that was in the possession of a Jew over פסח, pesach,
is that a rabbinic prohibition? That is rabbinic but it is true
that it still has no value. No value by rabbinic law. Right,
exactly. Okay, so let’s take a look at the גמרא. gemara. אמר
רב
פפא, amar rav pappa, said Rav Pappa, לא הזקינה הזקינה ממש, lo
hizkinah hizkinah mamash, when it got old that you now have to
pay the full value, the original value, it’s not literally
old like old and useless, אלא אפילו כחשה, ela afilu kichashah, even
if it just got weaker. Okay,
now again to assume that כחשה kichashah means that you are קונה
koneh it sounds crazy. The animal got a little bit weaker, you
are קונה koneh it? But again, maybe the only point is not
that you’re קונה, koneh, but just that you can’t say הרי שלך
לפניך harei shelcha lefanecha and you have to pay the difference. So
the גמרא gemara says, והאנן הזקינה תנן, ve-hanan hizkinah tenan, but our
משנה mishnah says got old, which is a significant amount of change.
So the גמרא gemara says no, כחשה כעין הזקינה. kichashah ke'ein hizkinah.
No, what our משנה mishnah means is not literally old, even getting
weaker, but a weaker that’s similar to getting old. What would the
weaker similar to being old mean? דלא הדרא ברי, dilo hadra bari,
that it’s not going to get better. So it’s not a שינוי
החוזר. shinuy hachozer. Okay? So it’s some type of, maybe it broke
a leg or something or some type of a thing
that it’s a permanent change. Okay, so if it's a temporary thing,
maybe you actually can say הרי שלך לפניך harei shelcha lefanecha and
give it back. If it’s permanent you cannot, even if it’s not
that it got old, even if it’s just that it got
somehow injured or somehow worthless.
אמר ליה מר קשישא בריה דרב חסדא לרב אשי, amar leih mar
keshisha bereih de-rav chisda le-rav ashi, so the elder Mar, the Mar
Keshisha, the son of Rav Chisda, said to Rav Ashi, הכי קאמר
משמיה דרבי יוחנן, hachi ka'amar mishmeih de-rabbi yochanan, here’s what they say
in the name of Rabbi Yochanan, אפילו גנב טלה ונעשה איל, afilu
ganav taleh ve-na'asah ayil, this is now the third time we’re saying
this in this מסכת, masechet, even if you stole a sheep and
it became a ram, עגל ונעשה שור, egel ve-na'asah shor, a calf
and it became an ox, נעשה שינוי בידו וקנאו, na'asah shinuy beyado
u-kna'o, now you have taken possession of it. And notice here it
says that it’s actually considered possession, okay, not
just for the following הלכה. halacha. טבחו ומכרו, tevacho u-mechoro, and if
you slaughtered or sold it, because this goes back to a גניבה
geneivah discussion, שלו הוא טובח שלו הוא מוכר. shelo hu tovei'ach shelo
hu mocher. So you
are slaughtering and selling your own thing, you do not have the
liability of four and five after this for selling it. So the
relevance for this is that you don’t need literally
הזקינה. hizkinah. הזקינה hizkinah means it’s a permanent change. This is also
a permanent change, a calf becoming a cow. But as I said
the other day, הזקינה hizkinah means that you now have no use
for it. It basically became like a worthless object, it lost all
the earlier functions. Here it actually
did not become worthless, it actually became something that now it’s actually
quite usable, it’s actually quite good, but nevertheless and it’s totally natural
change and that way it is similar to הזקינה. hizkinah. So this
type of a thing of a natural change is considered that it
now is a new object. Again, now one imagines that if, obviously
it has to be a qualitative difference. You don’t say, well, you
stole a five-day-old calf and now it’s a ten-day-old calf, you’re always
returning it a few days later. So there has to be a
certain type of a qualitative change and one of the things mentioned
here is שינוי השם, shinuy hashem, it’s called something different, and therefore
even though it was not through any physical action that you did
to it, it was natural, but now it has a different name
on it, so now it is like a שינוי shinuy and the
person owns
it. אמר ליה לאו אמינא לך, amar leih lav amina lach, haven't
I told you... לא תחליף גברי, lo tachlif gavrei, don’t mix up
the people. ההוא משמיה דרב אילא איתמר. Hahu mishmeih deRav Ila itmar.
That was not said in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
that was said in the name of רב אילא. Rav Ila. Okay,
but by the way that I think is less of a חידוש
chiddush than the משנה. Mishna. The fact that a calf that’s now
a cow, right, or a lamb that is now a ram, you
know that that’s a שינוי, shinui, that’s much more drastic than something
becoming old, I think, or you know, it’s certainly more drastic than
something becoming weaker, right? So all these things now are being categorized
together. And again, not to beat the dead horse or cow or
whatever, but the question I keep on asking guys, are all these
things cases that you can’t say הרי שלך לפניך? harei shelcha l’fanecha?
Right, that’s clear. Are all these things cases that you’re קונה? koneh?
That’s less clear. The case here about becoming a ram and becoming
a cow, there it said you’re קונה koneh it. The cases of
something getting old or something getting weaker, it never said you’re קונה
koneh it. It just said that you have to pay based on
the original value. Okay, so that’s again that space here in the
middle where you can’t say הרי שלך לפניך, harei shelcha l’fanecha, it’s
not the same, but it might not have changed drastically enough to
say you’re קונה. koneh. Maybe it’s a middle case where the owner
still owns it, but because it’s different, it’s not in the pristine
same condition, you have to pay the difference. Okay, so now yeah.
Is but you are putting a point in the middle of that
line because that’s just one point along a continuum. Right, but the
point is so far we’ve only been discussing the two ends of
the line. Right.
But the גמרא Gemara has not said explicitly that there’s that middle
point. I’m raising that possibility. No, it did. It said when a
lamb turns into a ram. Yeah,
it said נעשה שינוי בידו קנאו. nasah shinui b’yado knao. It was
saying that that was that case. That’s the middle point. That’s not
middle. That’s the aging continuum. No, I
fine, it’s a middle point in the aging, but I’m talking הלכתית.
halachically. All the גמרא Gemara has explicitly been talking about is saying
הרי שלך לפניך harei shelcha l’fanecha or being קונה. koneh. And I’m
saying conceptually there’s a middle case where it’s not enough of a
שינוי shinui that you’re not קונה, koneh, but it’s different enough that
you can’t say הרי שלך לפניך. harei shelcha l’fanecha. That’s this point.
How do you know? Where did it say? No, where did it
say that you’re? It said you’re קונה koneh it. I’m saying there’s
a place you’re not קונה. koneh.
The
גמרא Gemara by the lamb becoming a ram and the calf becoming
a cow said you are קונה. koneh. נעשה שינוי בידו קנאו, nasah
shinui b’yado knao, right? You are קונה. koneh. You are. That’s this
point, you’re קונה. koneh. Right? There’s one extreme, it’s so different your
object, you’re קונה koneh it. There’s another extreme, it’s the exact same
object, הרי שלך לפניך, harei shelcha l’fanecha, right? Can there be a
case where I steal your car and I bump the and I
and I bang the fender? Okay, you know, so
it’s not a different object, but do I get to say הרי
שלך לפניך, harei shelcha l’fanecha, do I have to pay you for
the difference? Presumably I have to pay you for the difference. Many
of the cases in the משנה Mishna which says you pay משלם
כשעת הגזילה mishalem k’shas hagzeilah are not saying explicitly that you’re קונה
koneh it. It could just be it’s a damaged object, it’s an
object that’s worth less, you have to pay the difference. So all
I’m saying is that idea that there’s a middle category has not
been said explicitly in the גמרא. Gemara.
No, are we not communicating? משלם כשעת הגזילה mishalem k’shas hagzeilah doesn’t
imply that you’re not קונה? koneh? The גמרא Gemara until now has
assumed it’s implicitly that משלם כשעת הגזילה mishalem k’shas hagzeilah means you’re
קונה koneh the object and you pay based on the value it
was when you stole it. Yeah, but that hasn’t said that explicitly.
And I
agree, it would imply this middle category. I agree that’s a very
reasonable read, but that has never been said explicitly. And a lot
of the times yesterday when we’re dealing with משלם כשעת הגזילה, mishalem
k’shas hagzeilah, the גמרא Gemara seems to implicitly understand that you’re קונה,
koneh, but not necessarily. So I’m just I’m just pulling that out
that משלם כשעת הגזילה, mishalem k’shas hagzeilah, why don’t I write that
here, there’s הרי שלך לפניך, harei shelcha l’fanecha, there’s נעשה שינוי בידו,
nasah shinui b’yado, and it’s possible that in the middle of there
is משלם כשעת הגזילה. mishalem k’shas hagzeilah. I mean, thank you for
throwing that out. That’s really what I was trying to say, that
that phrase in the משנה Mishna could easily mean you return the
object and pay the difference. It could mean that.
Okay, משלם כשעת הגזילה, mishalem k’shas hagzeilah, to return the object and
pay the difference. Okay, but it also could mean you’re קונה koneh
the object and pay the original amount.
Okay, alright, let’s now continue in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, רבי
מאיר אומר, Rabbi Meir omer, בעבדים אומר לו הרי שלך לפניך, Ba’avadim
omer lo harei shelcha l’fanecha, by a slave even though you steal
it you can just say here’s your slave back. Okay. אמר רבי
חנינא בר אבדימי אמר רב, Amar Rabbi Chanina bar Avdimi amar Rav,
הלכה כרבי מאיר. halacha k’Rabbi Meir. We rule like רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir that slaves are like קרקע karka and there’s no גזילה gzeilah
rules that apply to it. That’s for sure. Yeah, well that we
rule like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, yes. So the גמרא Gemara says
ורב veRav
says exactly that, ורב שביק רבנן ועביד כרבי מאיר? veRav shavik Rabbanan
ve’avid k’Rabbi Meir? ורב veRav is abandoning the Rabbis and going like
a דעת יחיד daas yachid like רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? I mean,
משום דברייתא איפכא תניא mishum deBraita itpcha tanya because רב Rav found
a ברייתא Braita that had the opinions reversed, that had the רבנן
Rabbanan saying that slaves are like קרקע. karka. So the גמרא Gemara
says ורב שביק מתניתין ועביד כברייתא? veRav shavik matnitin ve’avid k’Braita? So
why is he going like the ברייתא’s Braita version, go like the
משנה’s Mishna version that the רבנן Rabbanan are the ones that are
saying that slaves are not like קרקע? karka? So the גמרא Gemara
רב מתניסיה... Rav matnisiah... Yeah, well רב Rav had our משנה Mishnah
also in the reversed opinion.
So מאי טעמא דרב דאפיק? mai taama derav deafik? Now the גמרא
Gemara doesn't really believe he had the משנה Mishnah in the version
literally, literally, like the same ברייתא. Baraita. It understands that he corrected
the text of the משנה Mishnah according to the ברייתא. Baraita. So
wants to know why he did that. ומאי טעמא דרב דאפיק מתניתין
מן הברייתא? u-mai taama de-Rav de-afik matnitin min ha-baraita? Why did Rav
reverse the names in the משנה Mishnah to be consistent with the
ברייתא? Baraita? ואדרבה, ve-adarabba, let's say the opposite, ניפוך ברייתא מקמי מתניתין,
neipoch baraita mikamei matnitin, reverse the names in the ברייתא Baraita to
be consistent with the משנה? Mishnah? So the גמרא Gemara says, אמרי
רב נמי מתניתין איפכא אתנייה. amri Rav nami matnitin ipcha asniya. So
now it seems to sort of like repeat what it said before.
רב Rav actually, no, it's not that he changed the text of
the משנה, Mishnah, he literally had the משנה Mishnah that had the
different version, that had that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir was the one
that said that slaves are not like קרקע karka and the חכמים
Chachamim said it was like קרקע. karka. ואי בעית אימא, ve-ee bayis
eima, if you want I could say, you're right, he did change
the text of the משנה. Mishnah. So why did he follow the
ברייתא's Baraita lead and change the text of the משנה? Mishnah? כי
לא אפיק חד מן חדא. ki lo apich chad min chada. If
it was one against one, you wouldn't edit the משנה Mishnah on
the basis of the ברייתא. Baraita. But חדא מקמי תרתי, chada mikamei
tartei, one against two, אפיך, apich, he did reverse it. And he
found two ברייתות Baraitot that had the positions reversed. One was a
ברייתא Baraita that read just like our משנה, Mishnah, that said that
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said slaves are not like קרקע karka and
the חכמים Chachamim said slaves are like קרקע, karka, plus the following
ברייתא Baraita that also had the positions reversed. דתניא, detanya, we learned
in a ברייתא: Baraita: המחליף פרה בחמור וילדה, ha-machlif parah be-chamor ve-yaldah,
and similarly המוכר שפחתו וילדה. ha-mocher shifchato ve-yaldah. So somebody, you know,
swapped a cow for a donkey and so you gave me your
donkey, I sold you my cow. It works with חליפין, chalipin, you
didn't take possession of the cow yet. It was a pregnant cow,
we went to take possession of it, and when you went to
take possession it had already given birth. Okay, or similarly I sold
you my female maid, my female slave,
with money. When you went to take possession of her, she had
been pregnant, now she had already given birth. And we are debating
when did this birth happen? Before or after the sale took place?
Right, because we weren't there when it happened and the sale took
place sometime, you know, sometime along, you know, sometime in the last
two hours. No, the sale took place at noon. She gave birth
sometime between 11:00 and 1:00 PM. So we want to find out,
you know, when was that. Obviously if you bought the cow, you
want the birth to have taken place, you know, after you took
possession, and if I'm selling the cow, I want to claim the
birth took place before you took possession and therefore you did not
get the baby. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, so what's the
הלכה? halakhah? זה אומר ברשותי ילדה, zeh omer bi-reshuti yaldah,
the purchaser says it, you know, gave birth after it became mine.
והלה שותק, ve-hallah shotek, and the other one, so if the other
one says, so I don't know, so he's not making a claim.
Or זה אומר איני יודע וזה אומר, zeh omer eini yodeia ve-zeh
omer, excuse me, זכה בה. zakhah bah. So the one who is
making the definite claim wins. Because we basically say this would be
like a ברי ושמא ברי עדיף. bari ve-shema bari adif. One of
them says I know when it gave birth and the other one
says I don't know, so the one who says I know, the
one who is making a definite claim, he wins. זה אומר איני
יודע וזה אומר איני יודע, zeh omer eini yodeia ve-zeh omer eini
yodeia, they both say they don't know when it gave birth. So
יחלוקו, yachloku,
you divide the value of it. זה אומר ברשותי וזה אומר ברשותי,
zeh omer bi-reshuti ve-zeh omer bi-reshuti, they both claim it's definitely theirs.
So what's the principle? ישבע המוכר, yishava ha-mocher, so who is the
one that was the default owner? The seller, right, the seller at
one time owned it all. So the question is did the buyer
now, when he took possession of the cow, did he also take
possession of the calf? Where did, you know, when was the baby
born? So the buyer is essentially the מוציא מחבירו motzi me-chaveiro of
the seller, right, the one coming to claim something that had been
the seller's is now his. Okay, so basically, so the point is
it actually is a מודה במקצת. modeh be-miktzas. Okay, Jonathan there is
the buyer, I'm the seller. Jonathan says you basically owe me a
cow and a calf. And I say no, I only owe you
a cow. So it's a מודה במקצת. modeh be-miktzas. Okay, so I
have to take an oath that it's only the cow that he
has and not the cow and the calf. Okay, so ישבע המוכר
שברשותו ילדה, yishava ha-mocher she-bi-reshuto yaldah, I take an oath that it
gave birth before the sale took place and therefore, and I'm exempt.
לפי שכל הנשבעין שבתורה נשבעין ולא משלמין. lefi she-kol ha-nishba'in she-ba-Torah nishba'in
ve-lo meshalmin. Anybody who takes an oath takes an oath and doesn't
pay, right, in the תורה Torah an oath gets you out of
payment rather than entitles you to collect. דברי רבי מאיר, divrei Rabbi
Meir, that's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said. וחכמים אומרים אין נשבעין
לא על העבדים ולא על הקרקעות. va-chachamim omrim ein nishba'in lo al
ha-avadim ve-lo al ha-karka'ot. And חכמים Chachamim say no, there's no oath
that can be imposed on slaves. The case is, if they were
two claims, yes, I would have to make an oath in the
case of the calf, but in the case of the slave, I
don't make an oath because you cannot impose an oath on a
case of a slave. Okay, why? Because there is a הלכה halakhah
you don't make oaths on קרקע karka and slaves are like קרקע.
karka. So here we have a question,
so this whole interesting issue about the calf and when it gave
birth is not really our issue. Our issue is the debate of
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and the חכמים: Chachamim: can you take... Right,
because in this ברייתא *brayta* רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, *Rabbi Meir* says
you take an oath on slave, slaves are not like קרקע karka,
*karka*. In our משנה Mishnah. *Mishna* רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* says you
say הרי שלך לפניך harei shelcha lefanecha. *Harei Shelcha Lifanecha*, slaves are
like קרקע karka? *karka*. Everybody get how the רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*
position has reversed? Yes, in our משנה *Mishna* רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*
says הרי שלך לפניך harei shelcha lefanecha, *Harei Shelcha Lifanecha* by slaves;
they're like קרקע karka, *karka*. Here he says you make an oath
on slaves; they're not like קרקע karka, *karka*. So that's why רב
Rav, *Rav* reversed himself. Okay, so that we got. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says האי *hai*, הלכה halakha כרבי מאיר *halacha keRabbi Meir*,
so one minute, if רב Rav *Rav* thinks that our משנה *Mishna*
is wrong and that רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* really is the one
that says that slaves are not like קרקע karka, *karka* and we
rule like the חכמים *Chachamim* that they are like קרקע karka *karka*,
why does he say we rule like רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*? He
should be saying we rule like the רבנן Rabbanan, *Rabbanan* since he
actually claims that that is the Rabbis' position. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says no, הכי קאמר *hachi ka'amar*, this is what he means:
למאי דאפכיתו ותניתו *Lema'i d'afchisu v'tanisu*, based on your mis-reversed version of
the משנה *Mishna*, I believe the משנה *Mishna* has the names reversed,
but you think the משנה *Mishna* has רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* being
the one that says that slaves are like קרקע karka *karka*, so
based on your reversed version הלכה halakha. כרבי מאיר *halacha keRabbi Meir*,
we rule like רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, okay? But basically what רב
Rav, *Rav* is saying is we rule that slaves are like קרקע
karka, *karka*. In our משנה *Mishna* that appears as the position of
רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, but actually it's the position of the רבנן
*Rabbanan*, the positions are actually reversed and we rule that slaves are
like קרקע karka, *karka*. Okay, so that's what רב Rav *Rav* is
saying. Yeah, right. Isn't it just fascinating this question comes immediately after
רב Rav אשי *Rav Ashi* ties מר קשישא *Mar Kashisha* for reversing
the names? Oh, that's a good point, for introducing correctly. That's a
good point, I hadn't thought about that. Yep. Okay, yes. Why don't
we assume that they would have to be like קרקע *karka* in
all things? Oh, why do we assume like it's across the board?
Yeah, so תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* raises that question as well because if
you actually exactly understood, yeah, because one of the cases is where
I say do you swap the cow for the donkey, because the
ברייתא *brayta* has to draw a scenario where you didn't have the
object when it gave birth. So normally though chattel is sold by
taking physical possession. How could you get it without having it in
your possession? So one example is חליפין *chalipin*, that's what it gave
by the cow. But when it moved to the case of the
slave, it said or you'd sold the slave. Now why? Because slaves,
how are slaves sold? Slaves are sold not by משיכה *meshicha* or
הגבהה hagbahah? *hagbah*, slaves are sold by כסף *kesef*. But you know
why slaves are sold by money? By כסף *kesef* שטר *shtar* וחזקה
*v'chazaka* because that's how land is sold. So תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* actually
points out isn't it interesting that in the middle of a debate
about whether you take an oath on slaves, everybody agrees that the
way you take possession of slaves is the same that you take
possession of קרקע *karka*? So you know, do we make distinctions based
on categories? So if you take a look at תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*,
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says המחליף פרה בחמור *hamachalif parah b'chamor*, he says
אורחא דמילתא נקט *orcha d'milsa nakat* שדרך להחליף פרה בחמור ולמכור שפחה
בדמים *she'derech l'hachalif parah b'chamor v'limkor shifcha b'damim*. אבל אין לפרש *Aval
ein lefaresh* you can't say דלא מצי למנקט המוכר פרה בידו לפי
שאין פרה ניקנית בכסף *d'lo matzi l'minkat hamocher parah v'yado lefi she'ein
parah niknes b'kesef*, but a שפחה *shifcha* is ניקנית בכסף *niknes b'kesef*
because he says we're dealing with the possibility that slaves are not
like קרקע *karka*. But anyway if you skip to the answer he
says ומיהו קצת יש לחלק *u'mihu ktsat yesh l'chalek*,
it's like five lines before that תוספות Tosafos, *Tosafot* is over, line
starts with קצת *ktsat*. He says קצת יש לחלק *ktsat yesh l'chalek*,
דלעניין גזל ושבועה *d'le'inyan gezel u'shevua*, when it comes to this question
about like גזילה gezeilah *gezeila* or taking an שבועה *shevua*, נראה לגמרא
להשוות דתרוייהו נפקא עלי ידי כלל ופרט וכלל *nireh l'gemara l'hashvos d'tarvaihu
nafka alei yedei כלל ופרט וכלל klal u'ferat u'khlal*. Maybe when it
comes to questions about how do you do an act of קנין
*kinyan*, maybe everybody agrees that slaves are like land and you do
an act of קנין *kinyan* with like כסף *kesef* or שטר *shtar*
וחזקה *v'chazaka*, that's not debated. The question though is what we do
put in the same, not that everything for you know is all
one decision. Maybe קנין *kinyan* everybody agrees it's like land. So what's
the reason though to assume like Jen said that questions about גזילה
gezeilah *gezeila* and questions about שבועה *shevua* are the same? So תוספות
*Tosafot* says because that's when the exclusion of slaves is a little
bit more arbitrary. It's based on like this כלל ופרט וכלל *klal
perat u'khlal*. Like this raises the question: why is land excluded from
taking a שבועה *shevua*? Why is land not stolen? What's the basis?
Before we get to why are slaves like land, let's ask why
is land excluded from these? And most of the time it's based
on some דרשה *drasha* of a כלל ופרט וכלל *klal perat u'khlal*,
like it says כי יתן איש אל רעהו כסף או כלים *ki
yiten ish el re'ehu kesef o kelim* כלל *klal* לשמור *lishmor* פרט
*perat* כלל *klal*, you know כלל ופרט וכלל *klal perat u'khlals*, it
has to be דבר המטלטל וגופו ממון *davar hametaltel v'gufo mamon*, right?
Those are like classic כלל ופרט וכלל *klal perat u'khlals* we do.
It has to be cattle and of intrinsic value, you know in
those types of things, and excludes slaves and includes שטרות *shtarot* and
excludes, excuse me, excludes קרקע *karka* etc. So the basic answer is
you're right. As in many things you could make a distinction: for
some categories it's X and for others it's Y. And there is
actually a גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that does that in one place. But
here it's based on mostly these exclusions are based on some
דרשה *drasha*. If it's arbitrary, right, if there's logic to it, then
we'll assume, then we'll test whether the logic works in an individual
case. If it's an arbitrary formalistic question of are slaves formally identified
as קרקע, then we're going to be like consistent. Right, that's a
good way of saying it. Yes. Can you take possession of a
slave by moving
him?
No. It has to be כסף שטר חזקה. kessef shtar chazakah. Can
you do by הגבהה?
I'm trying to remember. I'm not sure. There might be some discussion,
but I don't think so. No. I think it has to be
כסף שטר חזקה. kessef shtar chazakah. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Okay, so now we've established that at least according to
רב, Rav he rules like our version of רבי מאיר, his version
of the רבנן, that slaves are like קרקע, and you know, as
Ginnock aptly said, in theory you could say it depends in different
areas of הלכה halakha how we treat it. But if this is
seen as a somewhat of an arbitrary category, then slaves are going
to either be in the category or not be in the category.
And now let's see how the גמרא Gemara's applies this to a
practical
הלכה. ומי אמר רב עבדא כמקרקעי דמי? U'mi amar Rav avda k'malkei
dami? Did רב Rav really say slaves are like קרקע? Now we're
going to, I mean we did the practical הלכה before about whether
הרי שלי חופשיאך, harei sheli chofshi'ach, but we're going to see I
think what I think is a little bit of a more interesting
application.
ואמר רב דניאל בר רב קטינא אמר רב, V'amar Rav Daniel bar
Rav Katina amar Rav, so it was said in the name of
רב, Rav התוקף בעבדו של חבירו ועשה בו מלאכה פטור. hatokef b'avdo
shel chaveiro v'asa bo melakha patur. If you basically seize your friend's
slave and use it to do מלאכה, melakha, you're פטור. patur. Now,
why is this relevant?
If קרקע, if slaves are considered נגזלת, nigzelet, okay, what happens when
I steal your cow? We just had this yesterday. I steal your
cow, I use it to plow my land, my land, and I
give it back to you. Do I have to pay you for
the use of it?
No. Right? Remember that's, remember that case yesterday? A guy stole the
cow, right? That's the principle, again, that's the irony of it that
we've been pointing out, but it's a principle that sometimes is called
קנייני גזילה. kinyanei gezeilah. By taking physical possession of it, that gives
me certain rights and means that I don't have to pay you
for the use. I just return it for you and I've exempted
myself from my, its responsibility. Okay. What if however I go and
live in your house without your permission and your house is up
for sale and I make use of your, you know, your house?
Do I have to pay you rent? So you might remember that
was a discussion earlier in the גמרא Gemara called זה נהנה וזה
לא חסר zeh neheneh v'zeh lo chaser or זה נהנה וזה חסר.
zeh neheneh v'zeh chaser. So everybody agreed if it was זה חסר,
zeh chaser, if the house was up for rent, you had posted
it on Airbnb, and then I was in it and I chased
the other people away because I was in it, I do have
to pay you rent. Right? I used your thing. It's a thing
that you normally charge rent for. My use of it caused you
a loss. I pay you for it. So why do I pay
you when I use your house and it's זה חסר, zeh chaser,
but if I steal your cow and I use it and you're
חסר, chaser, you can't use it, I don't pay you? And the
difference is, and this is the irony, since a cow is נגזלת,
nigzelet, since it's considered stolen, and that's therefore seen like I take
physical control over it, I become actually I have some quasi not
de facto rights to it because I've taken possession of it. It's
very bizarre. That means that I don't have to pay you for
its use. I'm a quasi-owner right now by force, and therefore I
get to use it and I just return it and I'm exempt.
Whereas by the קרקע, when I'm in your house, I wasn't, didn't
steal your house. I'm just using your thing without the right. I'm
not a גזלן gazlan on it. And I'm using your thing without
the right, and it's causing you a loss and I'm getting a
benefit. I have to pay you for its use. That's the difference.
So by house, if I use it, I pay you, especially if
it's חסר. chaser. By a cow, if I steal it and use
it, I don't pay you. What about a slave? I steal your
slave and I use him, and he does work for me. Do
I pay you or not? So the question would be is a
slave נגזל nigzal or not? If a slave is seen as like
a cow and it's נגזל, nigzal, I don't pay you for the
use. If it's seen as a house and it's not נגזל, nigzal,
then I'm using an object which I never technically stole, so I
have to pay you for the use. Okay, so let's take a
look. So did רב really say that a slave is like land?
Didn't we say, didn't רב say התוקף בעבדו של חבירו ועשה בו
מלאכה פטור? hatokef b'avdo shel chaveiro v'asa bo melakha patur? You're פטור.
patur. Which makes sense if it's like a cow, but doesn't make
sense if it's like a house. ואי סלקא דעתך עבדא כמקרקעי דמי,
V'isaka deitach avda k'karkei dami, if it's like land, אמאי פטור? amai
patur? Why are you פטור? patur? ברשותיה דמריה קאי, Birshutei d'mari kai,
even after you took the slave, it's still under the owner's possession.
It's not considered stolen, and you're using the person's property without having
stolen it, you have to pay for it. So that's a good
question. משני, M'shani, no, הכא במאי עסקינן, Hakha b'mai askinan, what are
we talking about? שלא בשעת מלאכה. She'lo b'shas melakha. That actually it
was a זה נהנה וזה לא חסר. zeh neheneh v'zeh lo chaser.
Technically you're right, a slave is like a house. And if by
you using it, you prevented him from working for his master, it
was a זה נהנה וזה חסר, zeh neheneh v'zeh chaser, you'd have
to pay. The only reason you didn't pay is not a, which
is a funny thing, because then the רב's real חידוש chiddush is
שלא בשעת מלאכה, she'lo b'shas melakha, like the key, you know, the
key criterion is missing. Right? It seems like Rav was saying a
blanket statement, you never have to pay. No, no, no, you really
do have to pay. It's like living in the guy's house. But
if you did it not at the time of מלאכה, melacha, it
was זה לא חסר, zeh lo chaser, then you don't have to
pay. Okay, שלא בשעת מלאכה. shelo b'shas melacha. שדר שלח ליה רב
אבא למרי בר מר, shadar shlach lei Rav Abba l'Mari bar Mar,
like רב אבא Rav Abba sent to רב אבא Rav Abba למרי
בר מר, l'Mari bar Mar, like רב אבא Rav Abba sent to
מרי בר מר, Mari bar Mar, בעי מיניה מרב הונא, ba'ei minei
me-Rav Huna, ask for me from רב הונא. Rav Huna. הדר בחצר
חבירו, ha-dar b'chatzer chaveiro, and here you go, exactly like we taught
much earlier in בבא קמא. Bava Kamma. If you live in your
friend's yard, שלא מדעתו, shelo mi-da'ato, without his permission, צריך להעלות לו
שכר או אין צריך להעלות לו שכר? tzarich l'haalos lo sachar o
ein tzarich l'haalos lo sachar? Do you have to pay him or
not? ושלחו ליה, v'shalchu lei, and they sent back to him, אינו
צריך להעלות לו שכר. eino tzarich l'haalos lo sachar. You don't have
to. So because it's a case of זה נהנה וזה לא חסר,
zeh neheneh v'zeh lo chaser, right? If it was זה לא חסר,
zeh lo chaser, if it wasn't the type of a house that's
open for rental, etc. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara is saying is
the חידוש chiddush here is not that a slave is like a
cow and you don't pay. The חידוש chiddush here is you could
have said the same case about a house. If you use your
friend's land, you don't have to pay him for it because of
the principle of זה נהנה וזה לא חסר. zeh neheneh v'zeh lo
chaser. And the case by a slave it would be זה לא
חסר zeh lo chaser would be when it's not the time of
מלאכה. melacha. So he says one minute. He says הכי השתא, hachi
hashta, what type of a comparison is that? בשלמא התם, bishlama hatam,
בין למאן דאמר, bein l'man d'amar, ביתא מיתבא יתיב, beisa meiseiv yasiv,
ניחא ליה. nicha lei. There,
he says, actually it is a חסר. chaser. If you remember the
גמרא Gemara discussion earlier, there were some type of a חסר chaser
even if you're not have the house listed on Airbnb and it's
not up for rent, there's a חסר chaser because, you know,
you're like your presence maybe is causing some damage, maybe it's preventing
me from using it myself, but the חסר chaser was counterbalanced by
some benefit you bring to my house when you're in it. What
benefit do you bring to my house when you're in it? So,
right, remember the גמרא Gemara's says the blackening of the walls was
a חסר. chaser. There's always going to be a little חסר, chaser,
even if you're not open for renting your house. But it's counterbalanced
by the fact of either ביתא מיתבא יתיב, beisa meiseiv yasiv, the
house is settled when somebody is there, right? Somebody who's there attends
to it, waters the plants, you know, just the you know, makes
people know that it's not an abandoned house. So that counterbalances the
slight damage that comes from the person's use of it. ניחא ליה,
nicha lei, so then I that's good for the owner. Or בין
למאן דאמר, bein l'man d'amar, or based on the approach of ושאייה
יוכת שער. u'she'iyah yukas shaar. Remember it said that there are demons
that fill the house when it's when it's vacant. So the person's
presence, you know, prevents those demons. So also ניחא ליה. nicha lei.
Either way, in a normal house that is not being listed for
rent, it's not a חסר, chaser, because there is a little חסר,
chaser, but it's counterbalanced by the benefit you bring by being in
the house. And that's why you don't pay, because ultimately it's a
זה נהנה וזה לא חסר. zeh neheneh v'zeh lo chaser. But he
says that's not true about a slave. A slave is חסר. chaser.
What's the חסר chaser by a slave? אלא הכא, ela hacha, מי
ניחא ליה דתיכחוש עבדיה? mi nicha lei d'sikchush avdei? Does it does
the guy want you to cause the slave to get weaker? You're
working my slave, this was his time off, you know, maybe he
was recuperating from the job I put him on, you're working him,
that doesn't do me any good. It's actually a זה חסר. zeh
chaser. All right? So everybody get it? So why are you exempt
when you use the guy's slave? If you treat it like a
cow, then it's like, you know, it's stolen, so a גזלן gazlan
doesn't pay for use. But if you're saying that a slave is
like קרקע, it should be like living in the guy's house. And
don't tell me it's not חסר, chaser, it is חסר. chaser. You're
making you know, you're working my slave when he should have some
time off. So the גמרא Gemara says, no. אמרי, amri,
הכא נמי ניחא ליה, hacha nami nicha lei, actually it's good for
me that you're using my slave. Why? דלא ליסתרי עבדיה, d'lo listere
avdei, that my slave should not, like, you know, get lazy. So
the fact that you want to go ahead and use him and
you know, and take and seize him anytime he's just sitting around,
that's actually something I prefer. You know, you gotta imagine what the
society like this looks like, right? There is you're walking by my
yard, you see my slave on his lunch break, you're gonna grab
him and schlep him into your house to, you know, to do
some work. Oh yeah, I want you to do that. All right,
anyway, so that's what the גמרא Gemara claims, that a קרקע is
not נגזל, nigzal, a slave is not נגזל, nigzal, and but you
should have to pay, but it's a case of זה לא חסר.
zeh lo chaser. גזונטהייט, gesundheit, I want you to use my slaves
at all times.
Okay. בי רב יוסף בר חמא הוו תקיפי עבדי דאינשי דמסיק בהו
זוזי, bei Rav Yosef bar Chama hava takifi avdei d'inshei d'masik behu
zuzei, and now we're going to see, you know, it's one thing,
you might say you're not allowed to do it, but if you
do it you don't have to pay. Now we're going to see
that it seems like it's like open season on slaves that aren't
working, you know? So it's like, you know, so the house of
רב יוסף בר חמא, Rav Yosef bar Chama, they would seize slaves
of people that owed them money, ועבדי בהו מלאכה. v'avdi behu melacha.
Okay, so Charlie here owes me money, and I see his slave
lying you know, walking in the you know, walking in the street,
and I grab him and have him come to my house to
do some work for me. Okay, now, that's not to pay off
the loan. So the גמרא Gemara going to get to the whole
problem about like ריבית, ribbis, right? It would be one thing if
I seized him and had him work for me and had that
work towards paying off the loan. But it's not that, it's just
like, it's incidental. You happen to owe me money, and I'm going
to now just seize your
slave. But that's a different categorical, I mean the weird we had
just said that maybe it's to my benefit that you use my
slave. But it seems if you're specifically going to the people who
owe you money, then it seems like it's some kind of right,
taking advantage of them or something. Right. I mean that's going to
be the funny thing, right. So and like why was it דוקא
*davka* those people that he was taking their slaves? It seems like
he was using some leverage in order to do that or you
could do it to people you're married to, which would mean it's
not. Right, that's a good point too. Right, so let's take a
look where the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* goes with it. אמרי רבה בריה
דרבה *Amreih Rabba breih d'Rabba*, so Rabba his son said to him,
why do you do this, stealing somebody's slave and using it? אמר
ליה דאמר רב נחמן עבדא נהום כרסיה לא lo, שוי *Amar leh
de'amar Rav Nachman avda nahom karseh lo shavei*. I mean this really
shows you like a very, you know, obviously it's not a surprise,
but obviously like, you know, a very negative attitude they had towards
slaves. Oh yeah, anytime a slave is not working, he's lazy. It's
always be of benefit to put him to work. So here's a
similar idea. A slave isn't even worth the bread in his stomach.
You know, slaves are worthless and not, you know, they don't even
they don't even work off of the food that you feed them,
you know. So any extra work you can get out of them,
they're just they're so lazy. It's, you know, it's all for the
good. אמר ליה אימת דאמר רב נחמן *Amar leh eimah de'amar Rav
Nachman*, when did Rav Nachman say that that essentially it was like
a, you know, like the master would want you to be working
the slave all the time, I guess, when did he say that?
כגון דרו עבדיה *kegon Daru avdeih*, like Daru his servant, he was
saying that because he was upset about one of his slaves. And
this one of his slaves was like a was like a good
for nothing. Okay. דמרקד בקובי *de'markid be'kubeih*, that basically like, you know,
dances a jig or something. How do they translate דמרקד בקובי *de'markid
be'kubeih*? Dances in the winehouse? Dances in the winehouse. I know it's
so racist in America like it's so. I know, I know. It's
obviously deeply disturbing but that's what we you know the culture. I
know, but yeah exactly. So he, you know, he said that because
he was responding to one of his slaves that he felt was
like lazy and just would dance around. אבל כולי עבדי מעבד עבדי
*Aval kulla avdei ma'avadei avdi*, all other slaves they do real work.
So how you can't say slaves aren't worth their food. Slaves do
real work. What right do you have to go ahead and take
somebody else's slave and use it for yourself? אמר ליה אנא כרב
דניאל סבירא לי *Amar leh ana ke'Rav Daniel sevirah li*, I hold
like Rav Daniel. דאמר רב דניאל בר רב קטינא אמר רב Amar
Rav, התוקף בעבדו של חבירו ועשה בו מלאכה melachah. פטור *De'amar Rav
Daniel bar Rav Kattina amar Rav hatokeff be'avdo shel chaveiro ve'asah bo
melachah patur*. You're exempt. Now why are you exempt? Why isn't it
a case of זה נהנה וזה חסר ze nehene veze chasar. *zeh
neheneh ve'zeh chaser* and that you'd be liable assuming that slaves are
like קרקע *karka*? אמר ניחא ליה דלא ליסתרי עבדיה *Amar nicha leh
d'lo listerei avdeih*. You see that if you're exempt, it means that
it's the case of זה לא חסר ze lo chasar, *zeh lo
chaser*. Why is it זה לא חסר ze lo chasar, *zeh lo
chaser* when I use somebody's slave? It must be that people want
their slaves to be constantly worked. And that's actually because rather than
their slaves becoming lazy. Okay, now by the way, just because we
say that it's a זה לא חסר *zeh lo chaser* doesn't mean
you're allowed to do it. Just because we say if I happen
to be living in your house without your permission I don't have
to pay you, doesn't mean that I'm allowed to live in your
house without your permission. Okay. But his claim is, look, because we
say you don't have to pay for the slaves and if slaves
are going to be like קרקע *karka*, the reason you don't pay
is a זה לא חסר *zeh lo chaser*. זה לא חסר *zeh
lo chaser* assumes that the master, it's considered good for the master
that I'm using their slave and that the slave shouldn't become lazy.
And that's why I think that A, I don't have to pay
and B, why I think I even have a right לכתחילה lechatchila
*lechatchilah* to do it, which is particularly surprising. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says anyway even if all that's true that it's good for
the master and it's a זה לא חסר *zeh lo chaser* and
you're allowed to do it לכתחילה *lechatchilah*, you still shouldn't be doing
it in this case. Why not? אמר ליה הני מילי היכא דלא
מסיק ביה זוזי *Amar leh hani mili heicha d'lo masik bi zuzei*.
All of that might be defensible if you didn't if they didn't
owe you money, okay, if you were not a creditor to them.
מר כיון דמסיק ביה זוזי נחזי כריבית *Mar keivan d'masik bi zuzei
nechzei ke'ribbis*. Since you have you have lent them money,
now you lent them money and now you're taking their slaves and
having their slaves work for you, that looks like interest. That looks
like you're getting a benefit from them. You're not having it pay
off their loan. You're just pocketing it. Okay, you shouldn't be doing
that. דאמר רב יוסף בר מניומי אמר רב נחמן אף על פי
שאמרו הדר בחצר חבירו שלא מדעתו אינו צריך להעלות לו שכר *De'amar
Rav Yosef bar Minyumi amar Rav Nachman af al pi she'amru hadar
bachatzar chaveiro shelo mida'ato eino tzarich le'aalot lo sachar*. Even though they
said that if you live in your friend's house without his permission,
again assuming that it was a case of like זה לא חסר
*zeh lo chaser*, הלוהו ודר בחצירו
*halvehu vedar bachatzaro*, if he happens to owe you money and you're
living in his yard, in that case צריך להעלות לו שכר *tzarich
le'aalot lo sachar*. In that case you have to pay him for
it. Okay, because even though technically you could say I'm getting something
that doesn't normally have to be paid for, and if it doesn't
have to be paid for it has a zero dollar market value,
okay let's not even if that's technically true, it still looks like
you're taking advantage of the person. It looks like you're getting something
for nothing, getting something as a result of your loan, even if
הלכתית *halachically* it's something that would not have you would not have
to pay for. אמר ליה הדרי בי *Amar leh hadari bi*. You're
right, I retract. I'll stop doing it. Okay, so again very interesting.
On the one hand this is interesting just from the principle of
what do you call it, of. זה נהנה וזה לא חסר ze
nehene veze lo chasar and putting that side by side to the
principle of about קנייני גזילה, kinyanei gezeilah, right? And this is really
an interesting נפקא מינא nafka mina of what it means that is
קרקע נגזל karka nigzal or not נגזל nigzal or slaves נגזל nigzal
or not נגזל. nigzal. One is the ability to say הרי שלך
לפניך. harei shelcha lefanecha I never took possession of it. If technically
I didn't take possession of it even though I schlep the slave
to my house and even though now it's a different object and
it's old and whatever, it's injured, maybe even if the slave is
dead at this stage, you know, I can just step away and
say okay, but you know, I never took possession, I never have
to give you you know I don't owe you anything. I just
walk away. That's one issue of אינו נגזל. eino nigzal.
The other issue is is that a גזלן gazlan because he takes
possession, his taking possession both makes him liable to pay, to compensate,
and to give back, right? That's one thing the act of גזילה
gezeilah requires which wouldn't apply by קרקע and slaves. I mean you
have to give it back because it's not yours but you don't
again have to replace it if something happens. Okay, so one thing
גזילה does is it requires compensation and replacement. But the other thing
גזילה does is it makes the person into a de facto owner
in the sense that he can use it without paying for his
use. That we saw yesterday. And that's what the גמרא Gemara is
now testing out by a slave. If I steal your land, if
I take possession of your if I take possession of your cow
and use it, I don't have to pay you. If I take
possession of your land and use it, I do have to pay
you in a case of זה נהנה וזה חסר. ze nehene veze
chasar If זה נהנה וזה לא חסר ze nehene veze lo chasar.
I don't. זה נהנה וזה חסר ze nehene veze chasar, I do
have to pay you off your land. What is the story by
a slave? So here we're saying that a slave is like a
land. Right so our earlier סוגיא sugya of זה נהנה וזה חסר,
now we are finding out there was a reason that was talking
only about land and wasn't talking about taking your car or taking
your cow because in that case you wouldn't pay because you're a
גזלן, gazlan, ironically. But when you're not a גזלן, gazlan, when you're
just sitting on it, then you would pay. Okay, and the slave
is like the land. Okay, and if we say the case of
a slave is a זה לא חסר, which is what we're claiming,
which is again, you know, like whatever really reflects a very particular
attitude they had towards slaves, oh the owner always wants me to
use the slave, okay, then because it's then that's why you would
actually also not pay for the slave, it's like living in the
house, it's a זה נהנה וזה לא חסר. Okay, so again, if
it was chattel, if it was a cow you would never pay
because you're a גזלן. gazlan. If it's land or a slave you
would pay if it were a case of זה חסר. ze chasar.
But we're claiming that the standard case is a case of זה
לא חסר, that the owner is not losing as a result so
you don't pay. Alright, and then the only remaining issue in the
גמרא Gemara was nevertheless that doesn't mean you can do it לכתחילה
and certainly that you shouldn't be doing it if the guy owes
you money, then it looks like ריבית. ribbit. Alright, תוספות has the
fascinating discussion which is
what are the things you're not allowed to do once somebody owes
you money or you know, could you not do things that even
if you would normally do? Like let's say, let's say a guy
would normally like, you know, lend you his he's your next door
neighbor and he would normally lend you his rake. Can you borrow
his rake if you owe if he owes you money? Because are
we going to say it looks like ריבית, ribbit, right? Can he
greet you in the street? say hello שלום עליכם. Shalom Aleichem. You
know, רב משה Rav Moshe has a שאלה sheilah of if somebody
can like write in the like in the beginning of a book,
can write like a thank you, you know, like an not an
acknowledgment, what's it called? A
dedication or something like that to people that have lent money towards
the publishing of the book. Maybe that's like ריבית ribbit because you're
publicly thanking the person, right? What are the types of things that
you can or can't do? תוספות basically says, something that you would
have done without the money having been lent, that would have normally
been something you would have done, like if you were my next
door neighbor and of course I let you use my slaves when
they're when they're not doing anything, that's a regular thing we do
with one another is we let each other use our slaves when
they're lying around and not doing anything, right? So then you could
do that even if you owed me money, okay or I could
do that to you whatever, you know, because but if it's something
that would not have normally been done, like then it's a question
of looking like ריבית. ribbit. But תוספות deals with that you know
important question, right? What are the types of things that look like
ריבית, ribbit, you know? It might be a favor you're doing for
me, but it might have been a favor you would have done
anyway. Yes, this is a really interesting question not just with the
ריבית ribbit thing but like to apply generally to positions of power
and things of drawing more boundaries when that's an excellent point. Right,
right, once there's that power difference even if it's something that you
would have done before it takes on a very different you know
sort of meaning in that power dynamic. Yes, so תוספות looks at
exactly that question. Alright, so now the גמרא continues, איתמר, itmar, was
taught. התוקף
ספינתו של חברו, Ha-tokef sefinato shel chaveiro, how about a boat? Now
is a boat is also a מטלטלין, metaltelin, of course one always
wonders what type of a boat? You know, there's like a little
boat, there's a rowboat, and then there's like the you know Queen
Elizabeth, you know, whatever, if you go by drive down the docks
there, right? At a certain point one imagines that a boat is
like קרקע, but anyway. Okay, התוקף את ספינתו של חברו, Ha-tokef et
sefinato shel chaveiro, if you seize a small boat, okay, a boat
of your friend, which is מטלטלין metaltelin ועשה בה מלאכה, ve-asah bah
melachah, and used it to do מלאכה. Okay you carried people or
whatever you did with it. אמר רב, so basically that's a case
of a גנב, ganav, a גזלן, gazlan, and you don't pay the
rent, right? So you're a גזלן. gazlan. So you're a גזלן, gazlan,
you basically just give back the boat and you're done. It's not
a case of קרקע, it's not a case of slaves. So רב
says רצה שכר נוטל רצה
פחת נוטל. rotze sechar notel, rotze pachs notel. If the owner wants,
he can get paid for the rental fee, and if he wants,
he can get paid for, you know, for any damage that occurred,
any depreciation. Obviously, he would take the larger of the two. So
the question is, why does he get to be paid the rental
fee? Why isn't it just a case of a גזלן? gazlan? Okay,
ושמואל אמר אינו נוטל אלא פחת. Ve-Shmuel amar eino notel ela pachs.
No, you only pay for the depreciation, which makes sense if you're
a גזלן. gazlan. אמר רב פפא לא פליגי. Amar Rav Papa lo
pligi. They don't debate. הא דעבידא לאגרא הא דלא עבידא לאגרא. ha
de-avida le-agra, ha de-lo avida le-agra. It depends whether this is a
normal thing that is a- is a standing thing to be rented
or not. How much, right, if I basically have a business where
I rent out boats, right, I rent out, you know, ten dollars
for an hour for the rowboat and you jump in my rowboat
and you use it for an hour and you come back, then
you have to pay, then I can collect the ten dollars. Okay,
but the problem still is, but if it's just סתם stam a
boat in my backyard, right, and it's not something that I normally
rent, so you know, why would you have a right to collect
like a rental fee? But the question is, even if I do
normally charge rent, why aren't you a גזלן? gazlan? So the גמרא
says אי בעית אימא הא והא דעבידא לאגרא. ei ba'it eima, ha
ve-ha de-avida le-agra. Even if it is something that I normally charge
a rental fee for. הא דנחית לה אדעתא דאגרא והא דנחית לה
אדעתא דגזלנותא. ha de-nachis leh ada'ata de-igra ve-ha de-nachis leh ada'ata de-gazlanuta.
When you went and you took my rowboat without asking me, right,
were you sort of sort of assuming like I'm not stealing it,
I'm just borrowing it, I'm going to return it, right, I'm just
using it. If that's true, here's the interesting thing. Because you're like
not a גזלן, gazlan, you're just using my boat. Well, if you're
using my boat then I normally rent it out, then you're implicitly
agreeing to be a renter of the boat even if you're, you
know, you didn't sort of agree to it. But because you're not
a גזלן, gazlan, you're not trying to take it for yourself, right,
you don't have the קנין גזילה. kinyan gezeila. Again, here is the
irony that the more you're a רשע, rasha, the more you're a
גזלן, gazlan, the less you have to pay. Okay, so if you're
trying to take it for yourself and then you changed your mind
or I caught up with you and I seized it back, so
oh, you were a גזלן. gazlan. As a גזלן, gazlan, you have
rights, de facto rights, and you don't pay me for it. But
if you weren't trying to take it for yourself, you were just
borrowing it, well if you're borrowing something that I normally rent out
by the hour, please pay me the rental fee, okay? You don't
get קנין גזילה kinyan gezeila and then you have to pay me.
So again, quite interesting that the less of a גזלן gazlan you
are, the more you have to pay for the use. All right,
now the גמרא gets to the case of שינוי shinui in the
משנה. פגמה טבעא ונסדק, pegama teva ve-nistak, a coin that got a
crack. אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, נסדק נסדק ממש, nistak nistak
mamash, a crack is literally a crack and then you can't return
it. נפסל nifsal when it's in- when it's been invalidated and you
can return it is פסלתו מלכות. pesalto malchut. The government has invalidated
it. After the Confederate War, all the- you know, the Civil War,
all Confederate money is invalidated and that's when you can actually say
הרי שלך לפניך, harei shelcha lefanecha. even if it's been invalidated. Okay,
now, even by the whole country. רב יהודה אמר Rav Yehuda amar
no, פסלתו מלכות נמי היינו נסדק. pesalto malchut nami hainu nistak. If
it's been invalidated by the whole country, by the whole, you know,
Roman government has invalidated these coins, then it's like it's got a
crack. Anybody looks at it, like it's clearly worthless money. Okay, it's
not something- even though it's not like a physical change, how we
see things also is impacted by our like, you know, interpretation of
reality. So it sees- we see it now as invalid money and
therefore you cannot say הרי שלך לפניך harei shelcha lefanecha. if the
entire gov- if the entire government has invalidated it. So אלא היכי
דמי נפסל, ella heichi dami nifsal, what's a case of being invalid
that you is not considered like a visible damage and you're able
to return it? So דפסלתו מדינה זו ויוצא במדינה אחרת. de-pesalto medina
zo ve-yotze be-medina acheret. It can't be used here but it can
be used in another like locale. So in that type of a
case, it's not completely invalid. It's not nobody will accept this money.
Okay? If you go ahead and you take this money to a
different type of- a different country, under the same, you know, Roman
Empire, but it's in a different country, it will be usable. Okay,
so that's some- so if it's nowhere, nowhere in the Roman Empire
can this money be used, then even if it's not a physical
change, you can't say הרי שלך לפניך. harei shelacha lefanecha. It's like
it's been damaged. Okay, it's like it's visibly not the same thing.
But if it can be used elsewhere even if it can't be
used here, it still is money, but just money that you have
to spend elsewhere. I mean I'm sure we all have somewhere in
our dresser drawers like all this, you know, currency that we have
from our various trips that's sitting there and like we treat it
as worthless until we happen to be going to that country again.
Right? You got fifty bucks but as long as it's, you know,
as long as it's, you know, somewhere halfway around the world, it's
like it's like play money until you actually have a time to
use it. Right? So is that- so that would be a case
that you could say הרי שלך לפניך. harei shelacha lefanecha. What?
Yes, and it's gonna become completely unusable. Yes, and that can happen
even if you hadn't stolen it. Why are you confused as to
why? Well, we're not making you pay because you caused the loss.
Like, we're making you. Well, first of all I could say maybe
the guy could have traded it before it became invalid, you don't
know how he could have used it. But the end of the
day is we're not making you pay because you caused loss. Then
there'd be a lot of cases you're paying for that you don't
pay. We're making you pay because you didn't return, you stole something
worth a thousand dollars, and you returned something that was worthless. So
I don't care if it was your fault or not your fault,
right? It's just that you did not, your act of stealing made
you liable to pay the, you know, what it was, the value
of the thing it was that you stole. The laugh's on the
thief. Well, yes, for once the thief loses out because you can't
make him say הרי שלך לפניך. harei shelacha lefanecha. Exactly. But it's
a good point, you're not making you pay because you're at fault,
but because you just did not return the same object that you
stole. Okay. So the גמרא says like this: אמר ליה רב חסדה
לרב הונא. Amar lei Rav Chisda le-Rav Huna. So רב חסדה Rav
Chisda said to רב הונא: Rav Huna: לדידך דאמרת נפסל פסלתו מלכות,
Ledidach de-amart nifsal psalto malchus, you say that even if the entire
Roman, you know, Roman Empire has invalidated it, that you could still
say הרי שלך לפניך. harei shelacha lefanecha. One minute. How is that
different than other cases you can't say it? הרי פירות והרקיבו, Harei
peiros ve-hirkivu,
when fruit becomes rotten, ויין והחמיץ, ve-yayin ve-hechimitz, and wine becomes vinegar,
דכי פסלתו מלכות דמי, de-chi psalto malchus dami, that's something that's like
completely unusable, that's like the entire empire has invalidated, וקתני משלם כשעת
גזילה. ve-katani meshalem kishat gezeila. And there you do have to pay
back based on how you stole. Basically, what makes this better? The
obvious answer is that this is not visible, that is visible. Let's
see what he says back. אמר ליה התם נשתנה טעמו וריחו. Amar
lei hasam nishtana taamo ve-reicho. Seems to be what he's saying back.
There actually you can use your senses, right, you know, the taste,
the smell, it is a clear, you know,
physical difference that has occurred to the thing. And therefore you can't
say הרי שלך לפניך. harei shelacha lefanecha, הכא, Hacha, here, לא נשתנה,
lo nishtana, physically it's the exact same coin. So even if everybody
looks at it as worthless now, it is still physically the same
object. You might say nobody considers it money anymore, but again, that's
not a physical change. And as long as it's not a physical
change, you can say הרי שלך harei shelacha, לפניך. אמר ליה רבא
לרב יהודה. Amar lei Rava le-Rav Yehuda. So רבא Rava now said
to רב יהודה: Rav Yehuda: לדידך דאמרת פסלתו מלכות נמי נשתני, Ledidach
de-amart psalto malchus nami nishtani, you say that when the Roman, you
know, empire invalidated it, that is like a crack, it's like a
physical change. הרי תרומה ונטמאת, Harei teruma ve-nitmeis, we have other things
that are worthless that are not considered a physical change. When תרומה
teruma becomes טמא tamei or you could say חמץ ועבר עליו הפסח,
chametz ve-avar alav ha-Pesach, דכי פסלתו מלכות דמי, de-chi psalto malchus dami,
that's now completely invalidated, worthless. Okay, not, I mean, it's not totally
worthless, you can burn the תרומה, teruma, but you can also melt
down coins. Okay? But it's a full status change. וקתני אומר לו
הרי שלך לפניך. ve-katani omer lo harei shelacha lefanecha. How is it
different? אמר ליה התם לא מינכר היזיקא הכא מינכר היזיקא. Amar lei
hasam lo minkar heizika hacha minkar heizika. Yeah, there it's not noticeable.
So here is really the גמרא did a beautiful job of explaining
what the debate is. Something that has no physical change, but it's
noticeable. How could it be noticeable if it's not physical? It's noticeable
because our way of looking at it has changed. Like you understand
that? Until now we've looked at this as currency and now we
look at it as a garbage, as not currency. Now again, it
has value, it could be melted down. So it's a non-physical change
that is noticeable to everybody. Right? It's a great, like the great
test case, right? Our way of looking has changed, not the physical
object. So one says that you can't say הרי harei... שלך לפניך,
it's not physical. The other says you can't because it's not הרי
שלך, we don't look at it as the same type of the
thing anymore. Okay. איתמר, Itmar, it was taught: המלווה חברו על המטבע
ונפסל המטבע. Hamalveh chaveiro al hamatbeia ve-nifsal hamatbeia. You lent your friend
money on a coin, or what does it mean המלווה חברו על
המטבע? hamalveh chaveiro al hamatbeia? There's a whole debate of רש''י Rashi
and תוספות, but I'll just tell you רש''י's Rashi's version. רש''י Rashi
basically says,
you know, I'm selling you something or you're investing in some project
of mine, okay, and we say you'll pay me ten thousand dollars
for it, but it's just not a case where I straight lent
you the money. We'll talk in a minute if I straight lent
you the money. I sell you some product or you know, I
make you, you become an investor in my thing and you owe
me ten thousand dollars. And now ונפסל המטבע, ve-nifsal hamatbeia, the coins
that were at the time that we were doing it are now
no longer usable. Okay, you know, the government has invalidated them. So
do you pay me, can you pay me with ten thousand dollars
of the old coins? No. רב אמר נותן לו מטבע היוצא באותה
שעה. Rav amar nosein lo matbeia hayotzei be-osah shaah. You owe me
ten thousand dollars, if there's a new dollars have been issued, you
have to pay me not the dollars at the time of the
transaction, you have to pay me ten thousand dollars now when it
comes time for payment. That makes sense. ושמואל אמר יכול לומר לו
הוציאו במישן. U-Shmuel amar yachol lomar lo hotzio be-Meishan. No, you can
pay me ten thousand of the old dollars, again, assuming that those
old dollars are still usable somewhere else, even if they're not usable
here. So this is exactly the case of פסלתו מדינה, psalto medina,
not מלכות. malchus. Okay? It's a coin that can't be used here
but can be used elsewhere. So we've been... what? Same worth in
the other place? Presumably, but but you know, you have to spend
the money to get to the other place, right? I mean, the
fact that it's not worth here means you know that it's... so
but yeah. So the course is, so similar to the discussion before
of can a גזלן gazlan say הרי... Here's the question: I owe
you money. Can I pay you with old money that was used
at the time of the earlier transaction that's no longer usable here,
but is still usable somewhere else? Okay, on the one hand I
can say, well, at the time of the transaction this was good,
and you can still use it somewhere else. On the other hand,
right now, it's not usable in this locale. Okay, so רב says
you have to give me usable funds here. ושמואל אמר יכול לומר
לו הוציאו במישון. veShmuel amar yachol lomar lo hotzio beMeishon.
שמואל Shmuel says you can go say, no, here, take it, it's
the type of money that was in currency at the time of
our earlier transaction, and I know you can't use it here, but
you know, go to מישון Meishon and use it there. It's usable
there. אמר רב נחמן מסתברא מילתא דשמואל. Amar Rav Nachman mistavra milta
deShmuel. שמואל's Shmuel claim that that's money that's considered paying up your
debt, that only makes sense דאית ליה אורחא למיזל למישון. de'is lay
orcha lemeizal leMeishon. That you're anyway going to be going to a
trip to מישון. Meishon. Look, you're going to be going to England
pretty soon, I know you got a business trip there in a
few weeks, you should be able to, you should be willing to
accept this money, you're going to be going there anyway. So that
makes sense, I sort of like the point I gave you about
money in your dresser, right? If like, if you're not going there
for like a few years, it's like, you know, as soon as
you're going there in a week, oh my god, this is like
a hundred dollars I have here, right? So as soon as you're
planning on going there, it really is considered legitimate currency. אבל לית
ליה אורחא, aval leis lay orcha, if it's not your plans to
go there, לא, that would not be considered legitimate payment. Let's just
read a little bit more, we're falling behind. איתיבי רבא לרב נחמן,
itivei Rava leRav Nachman, אין מחללין על, ein mechalelin al, you know,
I think we have to end. So we're a good deal behind,
but whatever, but it's already 8:30, so we'll pick up with this
tomorrow.